<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jake Connor on Jake Connor</title>
    <link>http://jakeconnor.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jake Connor on Jake Connor</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>HowTo: Get the Most Value from Your Engineering Degree</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/degree/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 23:58:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/degree/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A question you hear frequently from upper year engineering students is &amp;ldquo;How do I land my dream internship/job/career?&amp;rdquo; or variants like &amp;ldquo;I have X.Y GPA, why am I not receiving internship offers?&amp;rdquo;. Because I give this advice often, I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;replying to public&amp;rdquo; and describing it fully here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good engineer has a solid toolbox of skills and resources they can rely on to get their job done, and being employable means demonstrating to employers that you have those skills and resources.
Regardless of discipline, your toolbox should cover these five categories&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical Knowledge, Design, and Problem Solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience Building, Testing, and Fixing Products and Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project Management and Leadership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Strong Network of Colleagues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you put your head down, focus entirely on coursework, and earn a perfect GPA, which categories are you strong in? You&amp;rsquo;re probably solid in category one, but with the bare minimum in the other categories. So what should you be doing during those &lt;del&gt;4&lt;/del&gt; &lt;del&gt;5&lt;/del&gt; &lt;del&gt;6&lt;/del&gt; several years of a degree?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-course-work-falls-short&#34;&gt;Where Course Work Falls Short&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working hard in courses improves your skills in category 1. It builds technical knowledge and problem solving skills very well, and depending on your school can (but may not) do a good job of teaching the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But take a look at the other categories. When it comes to building projects, the majority of school labs and projects are standardized and repeated. You end up  solving the same problems as any other student, and have a TA nearby that knows the answer. Capstone project is often the only unique project you will do, and your only experience building a project of your own creation without somebody nearby telling you how things should be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times, over a full degree, do you have to stand up and present your design and your projects to an audience? It&amp;rsquo;s probably less than 10. If you narrow that to presentations where stakeholders are actively questioning your decisions and force you to defend the design, that number probably falls to 1 or 2. Engineering programs are woefully inadequate at developing graduates who can communicate and defend their ideas, and companies know this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of projects, how many of your projects have more than 3 members? More than 10? In my undergrad, the largest coursework project was only 5 people. At that size little management is required, compatibility discussions can be made on a napkin, and resources are easy to schedule. When head off into a career, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to find yourself working as part of a 20 person sub-team on projects involving hundreds of engineers, competing for resources with several other projects. And while it&amp;rsquo;s rare to go directly into project management at entry level, it&amp;rsquo;s important that you know how your actions and decisions affect the overall project, and that awareness doesn&amp;rsquo;t come from being part of a 5 person team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Networking, is completely outside your curriculum. It&amp;rsquo;s exclusively the domain of clubs, societies, and other extra-curriculars. You should make a few connections by studying with friends and working on projects, but that&amp;rsquo;s about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to completely devalue coursework, but it is not the only thing you should be doing. Coursework is mission-critical to getting that fancy piece of paper with your name on it, which is a prerequisite to Professional Licensing if your discipline expects it. But as the saying goes &amp;ldquo;C&amp;rsquo;s get degrees&amp;rdquo;, so don&amp;rsquo;t forget to focus on broadening your skill set beyond raw technical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extra-curricular-projects-and-engineering-teams&#34;&gt;Extra-curricular Projects and Engineering Teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These kind of projects are enormously valuable as learning experience, and your best opportunity to become a better engineer before you can land a co-op. You&amp;rsquo;ll be designing systems with a mix of the technical knowledge you&amp;rsquo;ve learned in coursework, while learning how to discover the things coursework didn&amp;rsquo;t teach you. Engineering teams will often have students working on tasks years ahead of their year standing, so you&amp;rsquo;ll be adept at teaching yourself, and have that background when it comes time to learn via coursework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve finished designing your system, you&amp;rsquo;ll almost definitely be the person who orders, machines, solders, assembles, and debugs your design. No TA around, no manual except the one you&amp;rsquo;ve written for yourself, and an endless stream of things that can go wrong. This stage never goes smoothly, and each build process teaches you how design things that are easier to build and test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects and teams provide numerous opportunities for improving your communication skills. From the formal presentations and design reviews, to being forced to defend your ideas during meetings discussing the path forward. These types of communications are orthogonal to your communications in coursework,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For project management there&amp;rsquo;s no better way to learn than with extra-curriculars. Every project in coursework is designed, run, and supervised by people who aren&amp;rsquo;t students. Once you join an extracurricular project, students run the show. Students manage time lines, schedules, budgets, and org charts. Students run meetings, hold training, and produce deliverables. Larger teams run like a business, with students managing outreach and public opinion, fund raising and sponsorship, purchasing, and operations. Small teams are great for first teaching you how to execute a project, but taking a leadership role in a large engineering team will be valuable experience for how to participate in and run projects in your future employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last but not least is networking. Because these projects are typically made up of the same students as coursework, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to immediately make a bunch of new contacts. But if the project is multidisciplinary you&amp;rsquo;ll build connections with students from other departments, and as you do outreach and competitions, grow your network further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;co-ops-and-internships&#34;&gt;Co-Ops and Internships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the bread and butter of your education. They&amp;rsquo;ll provide deep technical experience in design and in project execution. You&amp;rsquo;ll participate in meetings and present your work, while working in a properly managed environment. You&amp;rsquo;re not likely to be leading any projects, but will be closely working with other engineering and managers in your field, building a network of colleagues. Now, in some regions co-ops are the norm, and easy to earn. But there are plenty of regions where they&amp;rsquo;re harder to come by. If for whatever reason co-ops aren&amp;rsquo;t an option, there is a backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-work-with-professors&#34;&gt;Research Work with Professors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with profs is helpful, but not a complete replacement for co-ops. They&amp;rsquo;re a strong way to build technical knowledge and experience executing a project, while earning a (small) paycheck. You may or may not learn communication, but writing a paper of presenting at conferences is a valuable way to gain communications skills that are different from your coursework. Management and leadership are going to be lacking, given the small size of academic projects, and the fact that you&amp;rsquo;re likely to be on the bottom tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-70-20-10-model&#34;&gt;The 70-20-10 Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The The &lt;a href=&#34;https://trainingindustry.com/wiki/content-development/the-702010-model-for-learning-and-development/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;70-20-10 model&lt;/a&gt;
says that 70% of your professional development will come from hands-on experiences, 20% from interacting with colleagues, and 10% from formal education. It&amp;rsquo;s developed for people who have their degree already, so a little skewed, but a good example of where your priorities should lie. Work experience is immensely valuable and bets provided by co-ops, but also by extracurricular teams, and a little bit by research work. That social interaction can come from coursework, co-ops, teams, and research, but don&amp;rsquo;t forget to include things like conferences and outreach. Finally is the 10% of formal education. Before you graduate, that number is going to be far larger than 10%, but it should not be 100%. Finish your degree, don&amp;rsquo;t forget all the other important things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canadian International Rover Challenge Organizing Committee</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/circ/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 01:02:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/circ/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2018, Ive been part of the organizing committee for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://circ.cstag.ca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Canadian International Rover Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (CIRC), hosted each summer in Drumheller, Alberta.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Write Resumes as an Engineering Student</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/howto-resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 20:38:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/howto-resume/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I find myself giving a fair bit of advice about resumes to other students, some of which is non-conventional. To save repeating myself, I&amp;rsquo;m summarizing it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t relevant to experienced engineers, but should be useful for student trying to find co-ops or entry level positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cover-letters&#34;&gt;Cover Letters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of students ask, &amp;ldquo;Do I need to write a cover letter for every job?&amp;rdquo;. If you want the job, write a cover letter. If you don&amp;rsquo;t care about the job, don&amp;rsquo;t write a cover letter. The exception is career fairs, where cover letters aren&amp;rsquo;t common. In that situation, a targeted cover letter is a good way to stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-page-or-two&#34;&gt;One page or two?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives-section&#34;&gt;Objectives Section&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t bother. You are a passionate engineer who wants to change the world, and this is the ideal company to help you achieve that goal, &amp;hellip;or something like that. If you&amp;rsquo;ve written a cover letter, you should have already convinced them that you&amp;rsquo;re a good fit. If you didn&amp;rsquo;t write a cover letter, an objective section isn&amp;rsquo;t going to cover that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice is less standard here. Your education is probably not impressive. It&amp;rsquo;s even less impressive once you&amp;rsquo;ve graduated. The exception here is a top-notch GPA, and that&amp;rsquo;s about it. I believe even an excellent GPA is worth less than experience. My education section is at the bottom of my resume (as I&amp;rsquo;ve never had an impressive GPA in my life).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;experience&#34;&gt;Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the meat and potatoes. Now, you don&amp;rsquo;t need different sections for &amp;ldquo;Project Experience&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Work Experience&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Volunteer Experience&amp;rdquo;, or whatever. At most I&amp;rsquo;d have a section for &amp;ldquo;Relevant Experience&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Other Experience&amp;rdquo;, but I think its better to use ordering instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your experience need to be chronological? Somewhat. Start with relevant (engineering-ish) experience, in chronological order. If you&amp;rsquo;re including non-engie jobs (restaurant, sport), then below the relevant experience and in chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each item, don&amp;rsquo;t just talk at a high level what you did &amp;ldquo;built a racecar&amp;rdquo;. What specific parts did you work on, like &amp;ldquo;designed the wheels for a moon-buggy&amp;rdquo;. And the product lifecycle is long. Did you propose, budget, schedule, design, model, simulate, manufacture (yourself or hire a service), assemble, debug, verify, test, and write reports? All those skills are important, and especially the communications based ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineers have a habit of thinking that as long as they have technical skills, they don&amp;rsquo;t need the soft skills. However it&amp;rsquo;s more of the opposite. While many students have the technical skills (are fast learners, etc.), many lack the skills to write a proposal, produce a test report, or generate presentations for customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics and firm numbers are beneficial. Did you improve strength by 20%. Reduce mass by 5kg? Improve throughput by 1000QPS/server? It lets your potential employer know that you can actively contrast your chosen solution against others. Bonus points for proper trade-off studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: courses and labs are never experience. Projects that are part of courses are rarely experience. Capstone (senior design) projects usually count, but please show that you contributed something significant. If you&amp;rsquo;re not sure whether it counts, did you at the very least design, fabricate, verify, and test? If not, don&amp;rsquo;t bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-sections&#34;&gt;Skills Sections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re going to include a skills section, don&amp;rsquo;t just make it a list of bullet points. Include at the very least your level of proficiency in each, and if you have space, examples.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carleton Planetary Robotics Team</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 00:29:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was a founding member of
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://carleton.ca/cprt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carleton Planetary Robotics Team&lt;/a&gt;, a member for 5 years, and the leader of the electronics team for 2 years. During my tenure, the team built three rovers, attended four competitions in three countries, and took home two podium finishes. I now serve as an advisor to the team, providing guidance on both team management and technical decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since the team&amp;rsquo;s founding, CPRT has grown from a few space-interested students to more than 50 members under a matrix management system, with dedicated members to business activites. CPRT is on of the largest engineering teams at Carleton, and is the most interdisciplinary team within the faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first rover was nicknamed H3, and competed in Machester, UK at the United Kingdom University Rover challenge. The rover drove reliably and arm performed well, but was plagued by communications issues, as the competition was held in an urban location with a saturated 2.4GHz spectrum. Despite the issues we came away with a 4th place finish.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/cleared-it.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our second rover was named Waldo, and it was faster, stronger, and more agile than H3. A new arm provided 5kg of lifting ability at a full extension of 1.5 meters. Sparky could drive on flat ground at 2m/s, and tackle a 40 degree incline at speed. We brought Sparky to the first every Canadian International Rover Challenge, and took second place, falling short of first by a fraction of a point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/cprt/pushup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sparky does pushups!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Sparky does pushups!
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third rover, and the last one I was involved in design for, was named Waldo. Waldo brought custom-designed aluminum wheels and new motors for a new top speed of 4m/s (15km/hr) making it the fastest rover at the CIRC. The same reliable arm was improved with a 3 finger claw that supported infinite rotation, allowing the rover to use screwdrivers effectively. And Sparky&amp;rsquo;s 2.4 GHz communications system was swapped out for a 900MHz based one, which provided a full-data rate link even behind large obstacles (we tested through buildings and bridges) at 1km of distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team travelled to the University Rover Challenge in Utah, taking 24th place out of 96 competitors, and again the the Canadian International Rover Challenge, earning a 3rd place finish amongst a pool of competitors that now spanned four countries.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/cprt/Waldo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Waldo racing across the Utah Desert&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Waldo racing across the Utah Desert
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m no longer involved in day-to-day work at CPRT, but their &lt;a href=&#34;https://carleton.ca/cprt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; will include details of future rovers, events, and competitions. Because CPRT was such a valuable part of my education, I&amp;rsquo;ve transitioned into organizing the &lt;a href=&#34;circ.cstag.ca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Canadian International Rover Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, to help future students have the same learning opportunities I did.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Courses</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/page/edu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 19:12:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/page/edu/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/svg/edu.svg&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploying Hugo to Github Pages with Powershell</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Hugo_Powershell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 23:57:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Hugo_Powershell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently switch my web site to be a static site built with hugo and hosted on github&amp;rsquo;s pages. Being a statically generated site, hosted on somebody else&amp;rsquo;s computer, this setup is significantly more secure than my previous wordpress site, should be faster, and less prone to disappearing due to a server failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo has a quite useful &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/tutorials/github-pages-blog/#hosting-personal-organization-pages&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;explainer&lt;/a&gt; on how to host a hugo site on github pages, including the use of &lt;del&gt;magic&lt;/del&gt; submodules to maintain a source repository and a public website repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where they and I diverge however, is in the script to deploy. I primarily use windows computers, and powershell is more readily available than bash. So I wrote a powershell deploy script that roughly mimics theirs, and also commits and pushes to the source repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply saved this in my source repo as deploy.ps1, then hen I need an update, run &lt;code&gt;./deploy.ps1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-powershell&#34;&gt;#build site
hugo -t academic

# add files to git
cd public
git add -A

#set up commit message
$msg=&amp;quot;rebuilding site &amp;quot; + (Get-Date)
If ($args[0]) {$msg = $args[0]}

#commit and push public repo
git commit -m $msg
git push origin master

#and back out and commit and push source repo
cd ..
git add -A
git commit -m $msg
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inside a 260A relay</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/260A-relay/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:39:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/260A-relay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the fun things about being on a rover team is it gives me an opportunity to play with hardware far out of what I&amp;rsquo;d normally encounter. Much of that falls in the category of power, as we design for about a kW of draw running on 12V (for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A feature of our emergency stop system is a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mouser.com/ds/2/418/NG_DS_V23130-X0000-A001_0612-844233.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;260A automotive relays&lt;/a&gt;, which I recently fried. While disappointed to have ruined a rather expensive relay, I was excited to take it apart. Pictures below, and after that an explanation of what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/top.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My Tool of Choice&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        My Tool of Choice
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/top2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Top Off. Lots of Copper Here&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Top Off. Lots of Copper Here
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/side.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sides off. The far left copper is actuated by the coil, and the top metal acts as the spring. It&amp;#39;s bistable, so the copper stays where you left it after removing coil voltage&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Sides off. The far left copper is actuated by the coil, and the top metal acts as the spring. It&amp;#39;s bistable, so the copper stays where you left it after removing coil voltage
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/back.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The back, with contacts. Note the copper core in the coil. Did I mention it takes 3 amps to switch?&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The back, with contacts. Note the copper core in the coil. Did I mention it takes 3 amps to switch?
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what went wrong?

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/schem.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

Well, see those reverse protection diodes? Wired power up backwards. Rover batteries were happy to pump some 200A through them. The fix? A couple new diodes.

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/relay/the-fix.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Well that was easy.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Well that was easy.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PCB Bottle Opener</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/PCB-Opener/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 00:39:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/PCB-Opener/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So as far as I can tell, there have only been two written about attempts at making a bottle opener from a PCB, which to me is far too low a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nrahtW_ET8o&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brian Benchoff&lt;/a&gt; cleverly inserted a notch into an arduino board, though found that the design wasn&amp;rsquo;t very durable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YuPBHMznZMI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Low Voltage Labs&lt;/a&gt; came up with a more standard opener, but in a very small form. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find any mention of the opener on their website though, and wanted one of my own, so set out to create it from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/opener/rev1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;First Opener Revision&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        First Opener Revision
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because I like space, and thought they would tie into my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cprt.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rover team&lt;/a&gt;, I went with a rocket ship layout, and silkscreened the team&amp;rsquo;s information on the front. After modifying to include 2 per panel, we&amp;rsquo;re able to get 20 openers from Seeed Fusion for $10USD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were certainly some concerns about strength of the FR4, but after a suitable test campaign we are satisfied with the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some noticeable wear on the edge that hooks under the bottle cap, which may be mitigated by including copper and a pad at that location, and the horizontal size of the hole is a little too large. It should probably be shortened a couple mm to get firm contact with the bottle cap for leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design is open, and available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://circuitmaker.com/Projects/Details/Jake-Connor/CPRT-Opener&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Circuitmaker&lt;/a&gt; (which is lacking in handy layout features like mirrors, trims, arrays, and such) for anyone to fork and make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Make it a little less flimsy by adjusting the hole size (probably making the ship bigger)&lt;/del&gt; Rev 2!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate a sensor to light an LED when a bottle is being opened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a low power uC so the opener can count how many bottles it will open&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/opener/new.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Revision 2: Now With More Shiny&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Revision 2: Now With More Shiny
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organic Detectors for Radiation Detection</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 01:01:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my fourth year (capstone) project, I was part of a team that developed organic semiconducting alpha detectors. The team did not prove that the devices can detect alpha particles, but showed a high degree of sensitivity to light, which is a common predictor of success at detecting radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical radiation detectors are made from high purity Silicon or Germanium (HPGe), but have a couple drawbacks. The materials are brittle and inflexible, so any sensor must be made in it&amp;rsquo;s final shape. Additionally large detectors require weeks or even months of careful growth, with any impurities or imperfections reducing the efficiency of the detector. A major defect could mean scrapping the entire grown crystal and starting over, and these large detectors are highly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The organic materials we pursued are flexible, meaning we could build a detector and roll it into a tube, and place a source in the center, maximizing solid-angle coverage. Additionally the fabrication processes we use do not require careful crystal growth, and could be used to manufacture large detectors with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to the project was primarily in modeling the radiation interaction with our detectors. For alpha interaction, this was primarily limited to using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srim.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SRIM&lt;/a&gt; to determine a lower bound on the detector thickness, as alpha particles are easily stopped. Once we had determined that the lower bound for thickness would be constrained by the manufacturing process rather than alpha interaction, I moved on to modeling beta interaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y6.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For detecting beta particles, the model is more important.
Beta particles are difficult to stop, and if they&amp;rsquo;re traveling in a straight line, cover significant distance.
Fortunately for the detector designers, beta particles don&amp;rsquo;t travel in a straight line in a detector. Instead they bounce and ricochet around within the material, with their overall path curving, turning, or even doubling back on itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This path is complicated to model due to the speeds and interactions involved.
I implemented a monte-carlo simulation using the Bethe-Bloch equations at relativistic energies. The simulations builds a large number of potential paths through the material, and can the be summarized to extract bulk parameters.
These parameters include effective stopping power, range, and straggle, and directly support the design process for any beta detectors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antennas for Satellites and Space Probes</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/RF-and-Antenna-Design/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 01:02:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/RF-and-Antenna-Design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a year working at MDA Satellite Systems, in Montreal, designing antennas for various spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary focus was on communications-oriented satellites, with demanding specifications and tight uncertainty budgets. I worked on projects from the early proposal stage, through (successful) contract negotiations, and through the program phase to final testing and shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent significant time on Hylas-4 (pictured above), a High Throughput Satellite with 66 Ka-band user beams divided over 4 reflectors on 2 pallets. As part of the team I worked to develop RF mitigations for mechanical issues, determine assembly tolerances, and produced reports and presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I additionally developed a series of tools used to automatically perform tolerance sensitivity analyses on general spacecraft, and produced simple reporting data on performance effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I additionally produced a specialized version of the tool for steerable antennas, that automatically determined the steering compensation that would best mitigate misalignments, and extract performance metrics from the re-steered antenna. As well as being useful on any steerable antenna project, this tool was used to justify selection of cheaper manufacturing techniques on a large-quantity project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I worked on a series of internal tools, integrating functionality from many tools into fewer (minimizing engineering time running many programs), automating common tasks, and significantly improving the speed of other tools. In one case I improved the speed of a critical-path task by a factor of 4, where in many situations this task was the slowest part of a design iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shor&#39;s Algorithm, with Julia Examples</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Shors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:40:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Shors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the often touted examples of the power of quantum computers is their ability to run Shor&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm, which is a way to quickly find the prime factors of a number, and hence defeat many of the encryption schemes used today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many good explanations of how Shor&amp;rsquo;s algorithm works, like this &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.ams.org/mathgradblog/2014/04/30/shors-algorithm-breaking-rsa-encryption/#sthash.59iEnvXz.dHjm4gpG.dpbs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;more conceptual overview&lt;/a&gt;, this more &lt;a href=&#34;http://tph.tuwien.ac.at/~oemer/doc/quprog/node18.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mathematical explainer&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/0303175v1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; which not only explains the algorithm, but also the fundamentals of how a quantum computer operates. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to re-explain the algorithm, but instead I&amp;rsquo;m going to walk through an example, and hopefully give some insight into what the q-bits are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code in this post is written in &lt;a href=&#34;http://julialang.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;, and using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dcjones/Gadfly.jl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gadfly&lt;/a&gt; package for visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to play along, you can install Julia, or you can head over to tmpnb and create a new Julia notebook (I wrote this while using version 0.3.2). If you&amp;rsquo;ve installed Julia on your own, make sure you install Gadfly using&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;Pkg.add(&amp;quot;Gadfly&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then make sure you&amp;rsquo;re using Gadly in your session with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;using Gadfly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we&amp;rsquo;re ready to walk through Shor&amp;rsquo;s algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by picking what number to factor. For speed and simplicity I&amp;rsquo;m going to choose $m=21 = 7 * 3$. We pick a number $r$, and we will find the order of $r$ in the modular group of $m$, which is 21 for us. I&amp;rsquo;m going to pick $r=2$, but any number that isn&amp;rsquo;t already a factor of $m$ will work. (And if you&amp;rsquo;ve picked a factor of $m$ congratulations, you just factored your number!). Setting these variable in Julia (I will be using &amp;gt;&amp;gt; to show the results of these commands).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;m = 7*3
r = 2
m,r, gcd(m,r)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 21,2,1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we need to prepare our set of qubits. Just how many we need depends on a couple of things, how large our number $m$ is, and how accurate we want our answer to be. We will have a pair of registers, whose sizes we need to decide on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to calculate $r^a \mod m$ for many values of a, and the first register will contain our values of a. The larger this register is, the more accurate results we will get from our Fourier transform later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second register contains the results of the above calculation. Since the result will never be larger than $m$ we need at least $\log_2 m$ bits to store those numbers. so we set&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;mbits = convert(Int,ceil(log2(m)))
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the first register is still up for debate, but I&amp;rsquo;ll just make it 5 bits larger than the second register.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;auxbits = mbits+5
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 10
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re going to represent our qubits with a matrix, the value of the first register will be the index along the rows, and the value of the second register along the columns. This decision is entirely arbitrary, you can think of the qubit as a long list of cells, or a matrix of any shape, or even more abstract ideas. Since our 5-bit register is capable of holding values up to $2^5$, we have that many columns, and the same goes for the 10-bit register.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by initializing the matrix, note that we&amp;rsquo;re planning on putting complex numbers in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;qbit = zeros(Complex,2^auxbits,2^mbits)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This produces a 2-dimensional matrix, 1024 rows by 32 columns. Since every bit we add to $m$ doubles the size of this matrix, you can imagine why it&amp;rsquo;s not feasible to use this technique to simulate Shor&amp;rsquo;s algorithm on large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up it&amp;rsquo;s time to run the actual calculation for  $r^a \mod m$ on our qubit system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For $a=1$ we find $2^1 \mod 21$ is 2, so we put a number in the 2nd column of the first row. We do this for each row, and eventually fill in the matrix. However the question is, what number do we put? Since we need to preserve normalization (the sum of the square norms of the elements should add up to 1) we pick $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2^{10}}}$. So we can now run this operation, and take a look at the state of the matrix using spy (reminder, the blue cells are those that have a non-zero probability of being measured).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;[qbit[nn,powermod(r,nn,m)]= 1/sqrt(2^auxbits) for nn=1:(2^auxbits)]
spy(qbit)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/shors/a1.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can already see that the results are all arranged in a small number of columns, and if we zoom into the first 50 rows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;spy(qbit[1:50,:])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we start to see the pattern.

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/shors/a2.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much more clear here that the non-zero values are following a simple repeating pattern. In a perfect world we could just count off the period and use it in further calculations, but since we&amp;rsquo;re using a quantum computer we can only measure one of those cells, and not all of them. By taking the Fourier transform along the columns however, our qubit will then contain the period(s) of the function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where many people (including us) will diverge from the original Shor&amp;rsquo;s algorithm. While it is feasible to take the quantum Fourier transform of this entire system, it is much faster (and no less accurate) to measure the second register (along the columns). By making this measurement, we will then have only one column of non-zero values, which makes for a much faster Fourier transform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simulate making a quantum measurement, we start by finding the square norms of each column&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;col_norm2 = sum(abs2(qbit),1)
plot(x=collect(1:2^mbits), y = col_norm2, Geom.bar)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And taking a look at it, we see

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/shors/a3.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No surprise here, the columns with values have non-zero probabilities, the rest are non-existent. They have (roughly) the same amplitude in each, which means we&amp;rsquo;re about equally likely to measure any of these columns. We then pick a random number, to get some randomness into our measurement, and compare it to the amplitudes of the columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;rmeas = rand()
loc=0
for nn=1:2^mbits
     if rmeas &amp;lt; col_norm2[nn]
          loc = nn; break;
     else
          rmeas -= col_norm2[nn]
     end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point your results and mine will differ, that&amp;rsquo;s the fun of a random measurement. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry though, we should still end up with the same results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up we want to take a look at that last column. The first 50 rows look like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;plot(x=collect(1:100), y = abs(rem_col[1:100]), Geom.bar)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/shors/a4.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Again, we have a nice evenly distributed set of qubits. Now because we want to find the period of the pattern, we take the Fourier transform, and re-normalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;rem_fft=fft(qbit[:,loc])
rem_fft./=sum(abs(rem_col))
plot(x=collect([2:2^auxbits]), y = abs(rem_fft[2:2^auxbits]),Geom.bar)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/shors/a5.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we see we have a few large peaks, which we are most likely to measure later on. These are the dominant frequencies in the column we selected, and these are generally integer multiples of the period we&amp;rsquo;re trying to measure. So we make a quantum measurement on our remaining register, and then we can start working on guessing our period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;loc=0
for nn=1:2^auxbits
  if rmeas &amp;lt; abs(rem_col[nn])
      loc = nn; break;
  else
      rmeas -= abs(rem_col[nn])
  end
end

c = loc-1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where $c$ is our measurement of the frequency of the pattern. In a perfect world we could simply flip it to find the period, the period would be a perfect integer, and that would be that. However if you look at the plot above, you can see the peaks have some width, so there&amp;rsquo;s going to be some variance in what we measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we want to do is scan over a set of integer numbers $z$, and find the $z$ for which the value of $\frac{zc}{2^{10}}$ is closest to an integer. I will claim that the $z$ will be somewhere between $m-3\sqrt{m}$ and $m+1-2\sqrt{m}$. So we calculate the lower and upper bounds of this range, then classically iterate over the integers within using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;offset = ceil(m-3*sqrt(m))
diff = floor(m +1 - 2*sqrt(m)) - offset
dist = zeros(convert(Int,diff+1),1)
[dist[nn+1] = abs( (nn+offset)*c/2^auxbits - round((nn+offset)*c/2^auxbits)) for nn=0:diff]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can grab the index of the result closest to an integer, and account for the offset to give the value $s$, which is the order of $r$, the result we need to find the prime factors of $m$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a handful of methods to find the powers now, but the simplest conceptually is to find the gcd of s and m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;s = indmin(dist) + offset -1
agcd=gcd(convert(Int,s),m)
s,agcd , m/agcd
(9.0,3,7.0)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can see that 3 and 7 are the  prime roots of 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you&amp;rsquo;re following along, and didn&amp;rsquo;t get the same answer, try running the program again. The probabilistic measurements mean that the algorithm is not guaranteed to find the correct answer every time. Sometimes it might take a couple tries to get the right result, but thankfully the results are easy to check for validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Dual Numbers to Automatically Find the Derivative of a Function</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Dual-Numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 00:40:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/post/Dual-Numbers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imaginary numbers are a powerful mathematical tool, however most people are only really familiar with the commonly used $i=\sqrt{-1}$. This is fair, because $i$ has uses in just about any technical field you can name, but there are others which have their own uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dual numbers work by a definition similar to the complex numbers that $x = a + b\varepsilon$, where $\varepsilon$ is an imaginary number such that $\varepsilon^2=0$, but $\varepsilon \ne 0$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usefulness of dual numbers appears when you consider the Taylor series expansion for a general function using $a+b\varepsilon$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$f(a+b\varepsilon)=\sum_{n=0}^\infty \frac{f^{(n)}(a)b^n\varepsilon^n}{n!} = f(a)+bf^{&amp;lsquo;}(a)\varepsilon$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where higher order terms of $\varepsilon$ drop off because $\varepsilon^2 = 0$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In programming, we can take advantage of this to retrieve both the value of a function and it&amp;rsquo;s derivative, even in cases where we don&amp;rsquo;t know the derivative, or even when the function is a black box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example using Julia and the package DualNumbers, but similar packages exist for most common languages. The code below is a simple implementation of Newton&amp;rsquo;s method for root finding, which is a good use because it allows us to use both the function value and its derivative from each function evaluation. (Note that each function evaluation will require more operations than we would by evaluating with a purely real number. This is because adding and subtracting require 2 operations each, and multiplication and division many more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by defining the function under test in line 3, for this example it&amp;rsquo;s a simple quadratic, but it certainly doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be. Line 4 defines our dual number, this syntax lets us set $x=5+1\varepsilon$. We then evaluate the function at x, and store this in y. The variable y now contains a dual number of the form $y=a+b\varepsilon$, where $a=f(5)$ and $b=\varepsilon\frac{d}{dx}f(5)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual work of netwons method is in line 10, where we set&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$x^{*} = x - \frac{f(x)}{f^{&amp;lsquo;}(x)}$
We use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;real(y)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to retrieve the value of the function at x, and then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;epsilon(y)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to find the derivative. We then find the new value of y, and continue refining x until converges. The results are shown below the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-matlab&#34;&gt;using DualNumbers

f(x) = x^2 - 2
x = dual(5,1);
y=f(x)

@printf &amp;quot;\n\n%8s %12s %12s\n&amp;quot; &amp;quot;x&amp;quot; &amp;quot;y&amp;quot; &amp;quot;dy/dx&amp;quot;

while abs(real(y)) &amp;gt; 1e-8
     x = x - real(y)/epsilon(y)
     y = f(x)
     @printf &amp;quot;%8f %8e %8e\n&amp;quot; real(x) real(y) epsilon(y)
end

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34;&gt;
       x              y          dy/dx
5.000000   2.300000e+01   1.000000e+01
2.700000   5.290000e+00   5.400000e+00
1.720370   9.596742e-01   3.440741e+00
1.441455   7.779358e-02   2.882911e+00
1.414471   7.281571e-04   2.828942e+00
1.414214   6.625248e-08   2.828427e+00
1.414214   4.440892e-16   2.828427e+00

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that things don&amp;rsquo;t to end here. By implementing your vectors using dual numbers rather than reals, you can easily compute gradients of multidimensional functions, or even the Jacobian of a vector-valued function.
If you want to retrieve the second derivative of a function as well (perhaps to implement Halley&amp;rsquo;s Method), you can use Hyper-Dual numbers, which simply add another different $\varepsilon$, and have an associated Julia Package.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
