<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Jake Connor</title>
    <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Jake Connor</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 00:29:25 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Carleton Planetary Robotics Team</title>
      <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 00:29:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cprt.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carleton Planetary Robotics Team&lt;/a&gt; is entering its 4th year, and I’m proud to have been a member since its founding. The team’s primary goal is to build rovers for fun, and to compete at competitions like the University Rover Challenge, UK University Rover Challenge, and European Rover Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have had a couple false starts over the years, but this year succeeded in building a rover, and bringing it with us to Manchester UK, where we competed against teams from UK, India, Bangladesh, Egypt, and Poland. We were very impressed with the rover’s performance, and are looking forward to iterating on the design this year, and making many improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to get any new major project off the ground, and this team was no exception. In our first year we were designing for NASA’s Robotic Mining Challenge, but at the end of that year the competition changed its rules to prevent non-US teams from competing. We spent the following year in a state of limbo, hesitant to throw away the good work we’d done, but with little drive to move forward in the rover’s development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued working and learning, but did not physically build our design.
Last September, the team set our sights on the rover challenge series, intending to design a new rover from the ground up to compete this summer. We worked hard, and were able to make it in time for the UKURC, in July.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://jakeconnor.com/img/cleared-it.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I will return to my position as an electronics lead, after taking a year off while working out of town. The first goal of the electronics team this year will be to improve the assembly process for the rover, with better cable routing, cable color coding, and the use of latching connectors wherever possible. The last item there was spurred by an incident at the competition, where after carrying our rover from the hotel to the competition, a motor wire had come loose in a way that we couldn’t see with simple visual inspection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also be improving the testability of the internal electronics. We will achieve this by adjusting layout to make components easier to probe (in one late-night lab session my unsteady probe hand shorted a power module and fried it, requiring it be swapped with a spare), and exposing test points for components that aren’t easily probed. And since the team now has a completed rover, we will be running regular operation scenarios, which will open our eyes to more subtle problems and areas for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/N2haM_vvAiQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While my primary responsibility is in leadership of the electronics team, I have also been able to contribute from a design perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I developed the power architecture for the rover, including custom PCBs, and the assembly/testing/calibration procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fully functional power system can power on and off individual subsystems as necessary, and track the power usage and regulation efficiency at the regulator level. The system can scale to over 100 independent regulators, but presently uses 6 for simplicity and due to mass constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A personal goal next year is to separate the control and monitoring from the regulation, which will simplify the rover software and reduce the mass required per subsystem, which will allow greater granularity of control over the onboard power. I would also like to automate the calibration procedure, in tandem with the software team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also developed the rover communications link budget and hardware implementation. The rover uses 2.4GHz Wi-Fi for compliance to all competition rules and has 2 configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The short-range configuration is designed for a 250m range, and uses unsteered antennas. We can achieve a 54Mbps or better link at full range and when the rover is tilted by up to 45 degrees of pitch and roll, and any yaw. The 54Mbps is sufficient to fully control the rover while receiving visual feedback from 3 high-resolution cameras, or more cameras at reduced resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The longer range configuration adds a steerable high-gain antenna at the base station, and can support the above link up to 2.5km. The steering is done automatically using GPS feedback from the rover itself, and the rover is programmed to remember recent zones of good signal, and return to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://jakeconnor.com/img/the-claw.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Claaaaaaaaaaaaaaw&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The Claaaaaaaaaaaaaaw
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organic Detectors for Radiation Detection</title>
      <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 01:01:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my fourth year (capstone) project, I was part of a team that developed organic semiconducting alpha detectors. The team has not yet proven that the devices can detect alpha particles, but has showed a high degree of sensitivity to light, which is a common predictor of success at detecting radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical radiation detectors are made from high purity Silicon or Germanium (HPGe), but have a couple drawbacks. The materials are brittle and inflexible, so any sensor must be made in it&amp;rsquo;s final shape. Additionally large detectors require weeks or even months of careful growth, with any impurities or imperfections reducing the efficiency of the detector. A major defect could mean scrapping the entire grown crystal and starting over, and these large detectors are highly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The organic materials we pursued are flexible, meaning we could build a detector and roll it into a tube, and place a source in the center, maximizing solid-angle coverage. Additionally the fabrication processes we use do not require careful crystal growth, and could be used to manufacture large detectors with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to the project was primarily in modeling the radiation interaction with our detectors. For alpha interaction, this was primarily limited to using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srim.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SRIM&lt;/a&gt; to determine a lower bound on the detector thickness, as alpha particles are easily stopped. Once we had determined that the thickness would be constrained by the manufacturing process rather than alpha interaction, I moved on to modeling beta interaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y6.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For detecting beta particles, the model is more important. Beta particles are difficult to stop, and will travel far in a material in a straight line. Fortunately for the detector designers, beta particles don&amp;rsquo;t travel in a straight line in a detector. Unfortunately for me, their path is complicated to model. I implemented a monte-carlo simulation based on scattering cross sections and using the relativistic Bethe-Bloch equations for linear stopping power. This simulation allows extraction of useful parameters like effective stopping power, range, and straggle, and would support the design process for any beta detectors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antennas for Satellites and Space Probes</title>
      <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/MDA-Antennas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 01:02:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jakeconnor.com/project/MDA-Antennas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a year working at MDA Satellite Systems, in Montreal, designing antennas for various spacecraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary focus was on communications-oriented satellites, with demanding specifications and tight uncertainty budgets. I worked on projects from the early proposal stage, through (successful) contract negotiations, and through the program phase to final testing and shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent significant time on Hylas-4 (pictured above), a High Throughput Satellite with 66 Ka-band user beams divided over 4 reflectors on 2 pallets. As part of the team I worked to develop RF mitigations for mechanical issues, determine assembly tolerances, and produced reports and presentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I additionally developed a series of tools used to automatically perform tolerance sensitivity analyses on general spacecraft, and produced simple reporting data on performance effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I additionally produced a specialized version of the tool for steerable antennas, that automatically determined the steering compensation that would best mitigate misalignments, and extract performance metrics from the re-steered antenna. As well as being useful on any steerable antenna project, this tool was used to justify selection of cheaper manufacturing techniques on a large-quantity project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I worked on a series of internal tools, integrating functionality from many tools into fewer (minimizing engineering time running many programs), automating common tasks, and significantly improving the speed of other tools. In one case I improved the speed of a critical-path task by a factor of 4, where in many situations this task was the slowest part of a design iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Freescale/NXP Cup</title>
      <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/DOE-FreeScale/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2013 01:03:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jakeconnor.com/project/DOE-FreeScale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Waaaaaay back in 2nd year I was part of a team competing in the Freescale Cup, now called the NXP Cup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of the competition is that you have a 1:16 scale RC/car that must autonomously race around a track defined by a small number of painted lines. In my case the track was dictated by two black lines marking the edge of the track, and the only allowed sensor was a grayscale line scan camera, along with an onboard IMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using an ARM Cortex M0+ processor, the team developed drivers for the motor controllers (PWM), IMU, and camera. We implemented image processing algorithms to find the lines and convert them to the vehicle coordinate system. The lines were used as input to a PID control loop that managed steering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team as we started it only existed for a year, where we developed valuable infrastructure, produced a test track, and were the first Carleton team to attend a competition. The following year the challenge was converted into a capstone project for software engineers, and is now one of the yearly offered projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Optics Modeling</title>
      <link>https://jakeconnor.com/project/DOE-Optics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 01:03:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jakeconnor.com/project/DOE-Optics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Co-simulation of optical and electronic systems is an important topic, one which I worked on the summer after my first year, under &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doe.carleton.ca/~tjs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Smy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ideal simulation for optics would solve Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations, but the tiny time steps needed for full accuracy would be incompatible with the comparatively large time steps of an electrical system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we simulate the EM wave envelope, which changes at the same timescale as the rest of the electronic circuitry.
The envelope $A$ propagates according to the rather messy differential equation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ \frac{\partial A}{\partial z} + \frac{\alpha}{2}A + \beta_1\frac{\partial A}{\partial t} + \frac{i}{2}\beta_2\frac{\partial^2 A}{\partial t^2} = i\gamma|A^2|A$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of a team of 3, I developed a matlab simulator that models the EM waves in waveguides and fibers, first based on split-step Fourier methods, and then based on dispersionless differential equation propagation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model included coupling between forward and reverse modes, as well as reflection and transmission at the ends of the waveguide. We verified the model adequately modeled solitons, and even implemented and tested an interference based switch in the model by adjusting the waveguides parameters (in a real circuit, a waveguide&amp;rsquo;s index of refraction can be tuned by applying a voltage or by changing the temperature).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I programmed a small SPICE simulator based on Modified Nodal Analysis, including optical sources and detectors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
