<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Current on Jake Connor</title>
    <link>http://jakeconnor.com/tags/current/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Current on Jake Connor</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/current/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Carleton Planetary Robotics Team</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 00:29:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/cprt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cprt.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carleton Planetary Robotics Team&lt;/a&gt; is entering its 5th year, and I’m proud to have been a member since its founding. The team’s primary goal is to build rovers for fun, and to compete at competitions like the University Rover Challenge, UK University Rover Challenge, and European Rover Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we traveled to Drumheller, Alberta to compete at the Canadian International Rover Challenge. The team took 2nd place, missing first by a fraction of a percentage point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the team&amp;rsquo;s second rover, the first of which we took to Manchester, UK, earning a 4th place finish.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/cleared-it.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        H3 Clears a Series of Rocks at the UKURC2016
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was the electronics lead of the team for 3 years, and now having graduated, I act as an advisor to the team.
During my tenure, I designed the power architecture, link budget, wireless communications structure, and many customs PCBs. I managed 15 members of the electronics team split into 5 specialties, interfaced with the mechanical and software teams. I produced financial and mass budgets, managed purchasing, and negotiated sponsorships for the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since the team&amp;rsquo;s founding, we&amp;rsquo;ve grown from a few space-interested students to more than 40 members, having competed in multiple international competitions, and become one of the leading student teams at Carleton.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/the-claw.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Claaaaaaaaaaaaaaw&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The Claaaaaaaaaaaaaaw
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organic Detectors for Radiation Detection</title>
      <link>http://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 01:01:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jakeconnor.com/project/Organic-Detectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my fourth year (capstone) project, I was part of a team that developed organic semiconducting alpha detectors. The team has not yet proven that the devices can detect alpha particles, but has showed a high degree of sensitivity to light, which is a common predictor of success at detecting radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical radiation detectors are made from high purity Silicon or Germanium (HPGe), but have a couple drawbacks. The materials are brittle and inflexible, so any sensor must be made in it&amp;rsquo;s final shape. Additionally large detectors require weeks or even months of careful growth, with any impurities or imperfections reducing the efficiency of the detector. A major defect could mean scrapping the entire grown crystal and starting over, and these large detectors are highly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;caption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        An array of Schottky Layout Detectors in Alq3
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The organic materials we pursued are flexible, meaning we could build a detector and roll it into a tube, and place a source in the center, maximizing solid-angle coverage. Additionally the fabrication processes we use do not require careful crystal growth, and could be used to manufacture large detectors with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to the project was primarily in modeling the radiation interaction with our detectors. For alpha interaction, this was primarily limited to using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srim.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SRIM&lt;/a&gt; to determine a lower bound on the detector thickness, as alpha particles are easily stopped. Once we had determined that the thickness would be constrained by the manufacturing process rather than alpha interaction, I moved on to modeling beta interaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://jakeconnor.com/img/orgrad/y6.png&#34;  /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For detecting beta particles, the model is more important. Beta particles are difficult to stop, and will travel far in a material in a straight line. Fortunately for the detector designers, beta particles don&amp;rsquo;t travel in a straight line in a detector. Unfortunately for me, their path is complicated to model. I implemented a monte-carlo simulation based on scattering cross sections and using the relativistic Bethe-Bloch equations for linear stopping power. This simulation allows extraction of useful parameters like effective stopping power, range, and straggle, and would support the design process for any beta detectors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
